This is Wyatt, and on today's episode I was joined by Andrew McKenzie, founder of Agant.
Agant is building a GBP stablecoin with aspirations to branch into other adjacent products. I hope
you enjoy our conversation. Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures.
All of these expressed by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions and do
not reflect the opinions of Castle Island Ventures. Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the
assets discussed in this podcast. We should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this
podcast as a specific inducement to make a particular investment or follow a particular
strategy, but only as an expression of their personal opinion. This podcast is for informational
purposes only.
Andy, founder of Agant. Thanks for joining us today.
Pleasure to be here. Thanks for having me.
I have to check. You might be our first Scottish guest we've ever had on the brink.
Maybe. I know Nick obviously spent some time up in Scotland, so I guess he can maybe claim a
little bit of time up here. But yeah, I just need to remember to speak slowly and clearly as my mom
always tells me. Yeah, exactly. He gets partial credit maybe. Are you a Liverpool fan?
I try to stay in partial, so my dad and I, we support Leach United.
Nice, so a good season there too. Exactly.
Would love a personal background. Tell us who you are, why you're here. Would love to hear about
how you're involved in the crypto space. I guess my backgrounds have been quite the same as a lot
of founders in the space. I'm from an agricultural background. I grew up in the country, just north
of Edinburgh. I spent most of my childhood in and around farming, end up studying business
in agriculture at university, and then kind of just fell into my first job, which was working for a
large veg company up in Scotland, a grower manufacturer and distributor, and worked on
an OTC desk for them, buying and selling carrots and other soft vegetables like broccoli and
brussel sprouts, importing and exporting them in and out of the UK. So maybe a little bit of an
unconventional trading start to a career, but certainly one that I really enjoyed. It really
opens your eyes up to what drives markets. Do those trade on an exchange or over the phone,
or how's that happening? Purely over the phone. A lot of weaving and dealing, so to speak.
There's a few markets that you can arbitrage quite nicely. So yeah, it's just really interesting
start to my sort of finance career, so to speak, in terms of what drives markets and what fuels
the price action that we used to see. I didn't really get into blockchain, digital assets,
crypto, whatever we call it these days, until 2020. When the price of Bitcoin and Ethereum
disintegrated, my interest spiked, and then got hugely into DeFi in 2021, worked for a firm that
unfortunately became a victim of FTX, SAGA, so came out of the space and ended up going back
into traditional finance and worked for a firm moving funds cross-border for agricultural
businesses. So worked in the payment space for them, helping them manage the risk and also
remit funds. And I guess I very quickly realized that there's a really effective and efficient way
of moving value, and that is this thing called the blockchain. And that's really what sort of
fueled the start of what is now a GAN. What prompted a GAN? And what is it today?
A GAN is primarily a UK domicile stablecoin assurance and infrastructure provider. We kicked
things off 14 months ago now in January of last year. I guess it kind of was a combination of
reasons. So the UK as a financial center globally stands out. British pound sterling is the fourth
largest currency in circulation and the fourth most traded. UK financial services in London and
also across the UK have a global presence, but there are no pound sterling on chain. There's no
GBP on chain. And so I always felt like there was a need and it was an obvious thing to do.
And then in November of 2023, when I was still working in payments for ag businesses,
like I said, there was a much more efficient and effective way of remitting these funds. And then
I guess what came in at that time was Bank of England and FCA published the discussion papers
into the use of stablecoins in both retail and systemic payment systems in the UK. I guess for
me that was sort of the first catalyst to sort of starting what is now a GAN. The regulators were
ready to have the conversation. You know, a lot of my experience in digital assets and in crypto,
you know, weren't maybe the best. I was subject to a lot of grifts and stuff like that. I guess
everyone kind of was in DeFi. And so I really wanted to try and create something that was doing
things the right way when it comes to compliance and the way in which the business governs itself
and its ethos. That's really what we set off on. So I was involved in a couple of side projects
with some friends and we were on call some lawyers and I just pitched the question to them
and said, what's your abuse on a UK domicile, UK regulated privately issued stablecoin?
GBP stablecoin to be clear. GBP stablecoin. You know, we really tried to set out and creating
what we kind of call the most boring kind of stablecoin because we feel if there's going to be
a successful UK GBP ecosystem on chain, we need to have this foundation layer that doesn't do very
much that everyone can trust is, you know, transparent, secure and untrusted. What's the
current state of USD stablecoin adoption in the UK? It's quite high. We don't really have any other
choice. The figures aren't the most accurate at the moment, but somewhere between five and seven
million people own crypto in the UK and most of them hold, it varies depending on what their
total holding value is, but most of them hold somewhere between nine and 25% of those funds
in stable. So virtually all of them are in USD at present. And from your perspective, today there
being no alternative. You guys are attempting to build the GBP stablecoin. Are they owning USD
because they're trapped into doing so or by choice? I think it's a combination of things.
We've always viewed the crypto ecosystem as dollars. And I don't really think that that's
actually going to change in the short to medium term. That's where most of the liquidity is,
and it's where most of the liquidity will continue to be, you know, particularly in DeFi.
Where we've made a differentiation and it's quite pedantic, but we very much view ourselves as a
fintech that integrates and utilizes blockchain technology as opposed to a crypto business.
That's where we see the real value in non-US dollars stablecoins. It's not necessarily
directly providing liquidity against the majors. Yes, that might be a part of our business and other
UK GDP issuers businesses as well. However, you know, attacking the wider UK financial services
ecosystem, helping to solve a few use cases or problems for those organizations is where
we see the real growth in our proposition. And those problems you're mentioning,
are those highlighted by the rise of crypto and adoption elsewhere? Are the UK financial
institutions going to have problems because of crypto adoption or is it traditional legacy
problems unrelated to crypto that you guys are looking to solve? I think it's a combination of
things. I think we've put up with a number of underlying problems for quite a period of time
because as far as the industry was concerned, there wasn't really a particularly suitable
alternative that had the network effects that, for example, crypto has. Well, firms got very good
at putting clusters on old infrastructure and tying it together with credit lines.
They found ways around the settlement delays, etc. But, you know, that's reflected into the
counter party risk that they might need to carry or the amount of regulatory capital that they need
to hold to offset those issues. I guess to tie it back, Nick Vanenek always says that, you know,
if you look at FinTech for the last 15, 20 years, the front end of the UI, the UX, all of that has
seen massive innovation, whereas the back end hasn't. Whereas what we feel that both crypto,
blockchain technology and stablecoins present is that back end infrastructure layer coming up to
match the front end that we currently have. We've built this multi-layer convoluted system,
and the hope is that you'll be able to settle collateral instantly, especially when you're
doing this cross currency. I can't wait till FX hopefully moves on chain. What kind of inbound
are you guys getting? Who's interested to use this product? This time last year, we felt like we
needed to be a retail focused organization. We always felt like the institutions weren't necessarily
going to be ready. I remember going to the Digital Assets Summit in London in March last year, and
I think the theme at that point was the institutions are coming. And that's kind of what we felt.
Last summer of last year, we turned that on its head, and it was probably thanks to a couple of
the advisors that we brought in, and they said, really, the institutions are ready, and being
institutional first is really the avenue that you should pursue. Originally, our focus is very much
within the crypto industry, so to speak, in terms of what we were trying to speak to, exchanges,
to market makers, and OTC desk, everyone that had direct exposure to crypto. And then in the
autumn of last year, a couple of asset managers started to poke their head up. And that's where
things really started to get interesting, because we kind of knew that they were sort of dabbling,
but we didn't necessarily know how progressed they were in their own ideology and thinking in
terms of what they want to do for their own organizations, but also how ready they were to
start those conversations. So now, I would almost say there's been more that's happened since the
start of the year than happened in all of last year. Now, our conversations are across banks,
hedge funds, asset managers, payment service providers, electronic money institutions.
There's a whole spread. At that point, this time last year, we felt that stable coins were really
trying to solve problems within crypto, facing off against digital assets, or like you say,
maybe on the FX piece, because we kind of just viewed traditional financial payment systems,
particularly domestic ones, internal to the UK especially, as being solved. But what's become
really apparent is if I was to send money via faster payments, for example, to you in the UK,
it's free for me to do that. But if you're the infrastructure provider behind that,
if you're the institution that's providing that service, it's definitely not free. And so there's
a real opportunity as a stable coin issuer where you can turn something that is currently at cost
to that business into something that is a net contributor, a revenue generator to that business.
We're seeing a lot of interest, particularly in our inbound around that side, how businesses are
able to become a lot more competitive in some of the product offerings that they currently
aren't able to really compete on. And I imagine if you're a centralized exchange in the US,
you deal with USD stable coins operationally, and then users are off ramping into USD accounts,
that's relatively simple. But if you're a UK exchange today, and users are holding deposits
on the exchange in USD stables, and you have to manage that off ramp function and vice versa to
GBP, either the exchange or an on ramp off ramp provider is taking FX risk, because you don't
have that instant crypto or crypto settlement. So I imagine you guys could really be effective in
that flow. We see a lot of streamlining on the on ramp in particular, at the moment, it's kind of
a patchwork in terms of how you on ramp into US dollar stables. And like you say, you have that
FX that either use the user take on if you're holding dollars in your wallet, whether that's
an essentialized exchange or in your self custodial wallet, which isn't great. I at a point earned the
new SDC, I had to take on that FX risk. Luckily for me, there was a bit of political turmoil in
the UK, so the FX was going in my favor. But for example, you know, if you are a large financial
institution, a few basis points here or there can really make quite a big difference to you.
For them, it's a little bit cumbersome having to hedge out that risk. So being able to offer them
if they denominate themselves in British pounds, being able to be on chain and British pounds
makes a lot of sense as well. Do you think you see local currency stablecoins pop up around the
world in the next few months, a couple years? Yeah, we're starting to see that in a lot of the
conversations that we are having. And we're looking at how we can simplify the flows that
currently exist. For example, we're talking to a group of guys in Singapore, they're doing some
exciting stuff out there. And we were actually talking through those flows, you know, if they
were to send us Singapore dollars at the moment, the number of intermediaries that we'd each need
to go through. And we think that by taking it on chain, we can reduce that from a roughly five
intermediaries to three. So that's quite cool. And that's quite exciting. And also that's going
to take time to build up and to get that organic liquidity in there. But it's moving in the right
direction. People are starting to innovate in those sort of areas. And particularly between
like the UK and India, the UK and Global South, you know, the UK and Africa, Nigeria, Kenya, South
Africa, there's a lot of flow that goes that way. And so being able to do that on chain and like you
say, you know, being able to settle into stablecoins in those jurisdictions and not necessarily have to
do the off ramp simplifies the process drastically. How do regulators view crypto and a GBP stablecoin
as well as larger banks institutions that might have regulatory influence?
Stablecoins in the UK, to go back a step, are kind of split if that makes sense. And we have two
regulators. We have the FCA, which basically regulates all financial institutions. And then we
have the PRA, which sits under the Bank of England, which is the UK central bank, which regulates banks.
And so they are going down different regulatory paths. And they're starting to come together
and they're starting to talk a little bit more. And the understanding between the regulators and firms
and institutions in the sector is starting to align. However, there's still quite a long way to go.
The UK is behind other jurisdictions in terms of where it is in this regulatory process. We're
still at the discussion paper stage. The DPs and the SIs are still coming out. And we're still talking
about a lot of things. However, I do feel like there's a lot more clarity in how stablecoins are
going to be viewed. The FCA, for example, are going to look at them as a crypto asset and not as
e-money. And making those differentiations has been really important for not only us as an organization,
but also a lot of the businesses that we want to face off. Because really, at the end of the day,
they can have as much innovation and be as excited about stablecoins as they like. But if
their compliance and legal departments aren't willing to sign off, then it's not going to go
very far. I guess to sum it up, we don't have any regulation at the moment. We're trying to fit
stablecoins into existing registrations that currently exist. And I think that'll be about
a year or two away before we get any dedicated UK stablecoin regulations. So I guess at the moment,
we can backdoor through anti-money laundering, registrations, so to speak. But I would say
there is a little bit of hostility still there. But there's been a huge shift in the tone,
which is what is really positive. A couple of our advisors were at some roundtables
at Point Zero last week, and there was a lot of central bankers there. And again, they said the
tone of the conversation and the level of understanding is quite exciting and making
them feel quite optimistic. There's definitely a shift to being pro-innovation, crypto-friendly,
and trying to be one of the first movers within this as we go forward.
You must have some interesting conversations with powerful institutions, because I imagine
you speak to banks about all the things you guys want to do and are excited to do. And
you're probably in some ways worried, what if they decide they want to issue a GBP stablecoin?
Does that cross your mind?
It's a question that comes up almost every day. Someone says, what if the large incumbents come
in? You can almost split that conversation up into a number of different buckets, so to speak.
So if you look at banks at the moment, there's a real worry from the PRRA, which is run by the
Bank of England, the Dental Regulatory Authority, that regulated businesses could start offering
unregulated financial products. So they're really saying to banks, we need you to wait
until we have the clarity that we need, until we have the regulation before we can have you start
doing this. So it's not so that the banks don't want to, it's that they can. We've kind of been
making the most of that. But then if you look at existing stablecoin businesses and organizations,
I think a lot of them, with the conversations that we've had, they feel like there's still
so much for them to go vote after doing what they're doing at the moment, within the dollar
economy itself. There's still so much growth. So we're kind of operating under the radar.
I think there's a lot more traction within the UK and within GBP, within the last three,
four months, and there was even last year, the tide is really starting to turn.
Will they allow this innovation to exist, the British regulatory bodies? And I would say the
folks are probably lobbying there, or do you think there will be pushback?
I don't think there'll be pushback from the banks. I don't think there'll be pushback from the
industry itself. I mean, UK financial institutions have always been quite open to innovation.
That's refreshing. I wish we had that.
Yeah, maybe that's a slightly controversial view. I'm not sure. But if you look at, for example,
payments innovation in the UK, we were very quick to move to mobile banking, for example. We were
one of the first countries to start using contactless with the widespread adoption that we had. So
people are quite open to using new forms of money and new forms of payment systems. So
I think financial institutions, especially, can see the advantages. I think a lot of them were
going to do it earlier, in 2022. I know there was a large UK bank that was looking at doing
their own stablecoin and actually offering cryptocurrency purchases within their online
banking app. But then FTX happened and the compliance department just said, hell no,
we can't do any of this ourselves. So it's not that they don't want to do it, it's that they
can at the moment. How important is it that you guys are a UK-based company?
I think it's one of the most important parts of for us at the moment. Getting a local regulator
on site, you need to have a local presence, as particularly with the FCA authorizations
are globally recognized as one of the most trusted and respected regulators globally.
It gives us a few benefits. It enables us to conduct a few more activities, some of which
require local authorizations to do those activities. But typically, the regulator likes to use
local authorization as a condition for being able to undertake certain types of business,
particularly when it comes to facing off retail customers. And not only that,
it gives UK institutions a lot of confidence. This city is one of these strange places where
if you come knocking on their door and you're regulated through one of the slightly more
greater jurisdictions, their tails are automatically going to be up and they're going to be saying,
hang on, why you tried to circumvent what's already there. It gives us the ability to get
partnerships, particularly with compliance teams. Yeah, I imagine there's a comfort level that comes
with it. I'm curious for your perspective, being a stablecoin issuer, there's the traditional
business of net interest margin, you make money on deposits, especially in the context in the UK,
you've had innovation in the fintech space, you've seen new players in mobile banking,
you've seen new business models. How do you look at your best viable business model, long term,
or even more widely, what the best business model for someone taking on this opportunity
of new currency stablecoin? The net interest margin is always going to be a factor. I think
what's lucky for us at the moment is that the FCA has said that no interest shall be given to the
token holder. They don't want yield bearing stablecoins to be a thing. Interesting. They
proactively said that? Yeah, they all kind of at the moment want to always be one. However,
I think as our business develops and changes and grows, we don't want to necessarily just be
relying on that because you're basically one line within a piece of regulation away from your
entire business model, beating no longer existing. We see a lot on the transaction fee side. We actually
see a lot on the banking element as well. If you're able to access deposited funds, you can
potentially offer banking services to corporates like lending payments, but then also on the yield
bearing side as well, we see a lot of opportunity there. I think regulators are more open to a
new bank than an organization like us progressing into something that looks very like a bank as
opposed to an existing bank starting to offer new forms of business. They're a little bit cagey
about the contagion risk that sits there. UK banks have real uphill battle with regulators,
and that's something that I think we as an organization can capture within our own business
model. I think over time, we would quite like a gantt to start looking more like a bank and the
types of banking services that we'd be able to offer, we can generate revenue from that.
With regulatory considerations in mind, how do you look at launching on private blockchains
versus permissionless blockchains? I think they all have their place, and we talked to some asset
managers that want to solve use stablecoins to solve an internal use case. Whether that's on a
public ledger or a private ledger is neither here nor there. However, I'm a strong believer that we
should be on public blockchains as much as we can. I think when you see a lot of the innovations in
being able to hide transactions and shield vulnerabilities all the way, we want a degree
of transparency, but there are times and places where that transparency isn't good. There's certain
networks out there that are really innovating in that space and making it quite exciting for us
to be a part of that. Going to institutions, we can see the value proposition of both.
That's a personal viewpoint to be clear, the preference for permissionless blockchains.
No, that is a personal preference. I think there's a lot of advantages to public permissionless
technology. What other product directions are you excited about, potential adjacencies?
We get really excited about being able to generate sustainable risk-adjusted returns.
I know that sounds quite a mouthful, but I feel like a lot of the returns in DeFi
aren't particularly sustainable long-term. I think being able to bring real-world returns
and distribute them on chain, things get quite exciting. It's quite apparent that if you're
going to take financial services on chain, the risk-free rate isn't necessarily attractive enough,
and so you need to be offering something that's slightly more enhanced, a few percent more. Being
able to do that is something that we get quite excited about, but then there's different aspects.
I was having a conversation earlier today about effectively creating funds of funds where you
can diversify out that risk. Risk-weighted returns on chain where people can see enhanced returns
without necessarily having to take on incredible amounts of risk. I personally get quite excited
about that side of things. Yeah, it's interesting because I feel like we've built two opposite
sides of the coin in that you have savings accounts, almost traditional bank accounts,
which allow you to hold money very well, and then you have the highly speculative DeFi yield side,
but the middle ground is not that well-served. You've Goldman Sachs high yield savings accounts
in some equivalents, but it still feels like, to your point, attractive steady rate investment
products are somewhat gate-kept. 100%. A lot of these organizations and funds that maybe offer
these financial products, like you say, the minimum ticket might be £10 million. We were able to
come in and we were able to act as the LP for those organizations, and then we can effectively
fractionalize our stake within them. We're effectively democratizing those returns because,
in reality, if you're able to take, let's say somewhere between 8% and 12% annually,
the returns are completely uncorrelated to financial markets and the level of risk that
you're taking is significantly lower than that within traditional financial markets.
That's quite an attractive proposition for a lot of people and a lot of organizations.
If you look at USD stablecoins and how they eventually came to what I'd consider now rapidly
growing adoption, there was a pretty slow bleed for a while. You had them come into existence
and it took a while to get to $10 million, $20 million in total supply. Do you think that will
be the same process we see with a GBP stablecoin and other alternatives, and then we'll have an
inflection and that's for rapid growth we see with USD today? Not really when we launch, hopefully,
in the next few months. I don't think our growth will be by and means linear,
but I don't think it will be slow initially because I do think there is a base-level demand
that really wants a financial product on chain that isn't necessarily dollars. I think initially,
for us to get to a circle or a teller kind of size, then yeah, that's going to take a while
and there probably will need to be an inflection point that we would consider as reaching mass
adoption. However, for us to get to a modest size with a few commas and zeros, I honestly don't
believe that that's going to be particularly long for us. The types of conversations that we're
having and the types of organizations that are reaching out to us demonstrates that there is
this demand. I think that's one thing that has been quite surprising is how easily we've been
able to have a lot of the conversations that we're currently having. What Dollar Stablecoins has done
for us is they demonstrate the proof is in the pudding. What's also quite helpful for us is that
global financial markets, while the majority is dollars, there's a lot of value that's also not.
The UK financial ecosystem, the whole industry, a lot of that's not dollars, but a lot of the
use cases can be applied directly to those organizations. We're feeling pretty optimistic
about our trajectory and also that for the industry as a whole. To your point, I think there is and
will continue to be demand. Who do you think are the winners and losers once you guys are at scale
and other comparable players are at scale? I sat on a panel a few weeks ago in front of a bunch
of bankers and I basically said, you need to start embracing this or you're going to become a victim
of it. I would say if I was any financial institution, you know, the investment banks and
the investment banks on the whole, if they manage their risks, they're going to survive in one firm
or another. Where I would be nervous is if I was within the retail banking system. If I'm an individual
within the UK, for example, and I have my savings with a standard high street retail bank, I'm only
covered up to 85,000 pounds. Anything more than that, I'm subject to the bank's own risks and
its own reserves. They're fractionally backed. And if I could be fully backed, I would choose to be
fully backed, not fractionally backed. So yeah, I think the UK retail banking system is probably
the most at risk, although I'm sure the regulators will find ways to protect them if they need to.
Presumably, these yield very interesting products will be interesting for them,
though, at least as business models that they can almost leech onto.
I think so. And I think maybe that's what we start to do is view them as a distribution
channel, look at how we can integrate. I do think that there'll come a point where a lot of these
financial institutions will turn around and say, well, if we can't beat them, we'll join them.
Otherwise, they will be put under significant pressure.
Longer term, do you guys want to be one flagship product more akin to a circle,
or do you want to be a suite of products or somewhere in the middle when it comes to how
many tokens and on-chain offerings you have? I think we're organically finding that out ourselves.
I mean, we initially wanted to start as this retail on and off ramp that was integrated with
open banking and automated KYC and AML to make this seamless interoperability between
and pounds on chain. And I guess as we've sort of developed as individuals and as an organisation,
we've seen that change between client demand and also our own ideas.
I think yield products on chain make a lot of sense. And I guess we've kind of seen that with
what circle is doing with their acquisition of Hational. I think for us, we will have quite
a narrow suite of products. We would rather have quality over quantity. I think there's a requirement
for stablecoin issuers to not just be an issuer and to be a really good quality infrastructure
provider as well. Because at the end of the day, if you want organisations to integrate and build
on top of your product, you need to make it particularly easy and attractive for them to
do that work. I wanted to ask you one final question, which is what is the user behaviour
change you're seeing at the moment that makes you compelled that this is going to happen or
what makes you excited that you're seeing in the market? I think for us, it's the level of
willingness of high level individuals in organisations that we would probably consider as
not really being particularly forward thinking or innovative, being willing and open to have
these conversations, looking to move at a pace that we would consider to be quite fast for them
and the level of ideation that they have themselves. I think it's very easy for us to say that a lot
of financial institutions and also large corporates are quite behind the curve but
I actually don't think they are. I think a lot of them are thinking about this and so that gives us
a lot of motivation, particularly in the level of inbound that we're also receiving. I don't feel
like we've got a huge uphill battle on finding good quality distribution partners there out there
and it's up to us to deliver a commercial situation that works well for both parties.
It's good to hear people are listening. It's been a pleasure having you on. Thanks for joining us.
Thanks for having me. Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island.
To find out more about Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc. To listen to all of our podcast
episodes, please go to onthebrink-podcast.com or just click on the tab in our website.
Thanks for listening.